If you're not from the fitness industry,
you're probably wondering by now, why is
it that so many personal trainers
are becoming multimillionaires before
their
40s? Well, actually, the reality
is pretty straightforward
when you think about it,
and I'm going to break it down so
that you can apply this to your own
business
whether you work in fitness or not.
Now, the first two things
are written on the board behind me,
and we're going to
start here with progressive overload.
Now, funnily enough, I know
when I look at the retention graphs for
this video,
this is where people
are going to choose to leave.
They're going to go, "I know what
that means." But quickly,
for those of you that
haven't heard the term before,
think about this.
You walk past my gym,
and you see me in here training my nan.
Now, whether it's my nan
or anyone in the planet,
my job as a personal trainer is
to determine one thing,
and this very one thing
is the exact same thing I do as a
business coach. It
is to determine where you are at now.
Not to judge you for it.
We just need to know where you are now.
Everyone that came to me as a personal
trainer would start in a slightly
different
place,
and maybe my nan would begin by sitting up
and standing up on a
plyometric box.
And although to most people this might
seem relatively easy and
straightforward, for her,
it could be incredibly challenging.
There are going to be nuances between
everyone wherever they are. Stay with me.
My job as a trainer was to say, "Okay,
I've given you this.
How hard was it out of 10?" My nan says,
"About an eight or a nine." I know we're
in the sweet spot.
If she says it's only a five or a six,
I know I need to make the
box lower.
And if she doesn't complete the reps,
I know it's too hard.
My job is to give her what she can do at
the upper echelon of difficulty.
Then over time,
I'm going to change it to make it more
difficult.
And there are plenty of ways as a trainer
that we can make an exercise more
difficult. I can make the box lower.
I can make the reps higher.
I can give her a weight, whatever.
So what's that got to do with you?
Well,
whether or not you've got 100 followers,
1,000 followers, 10,000 followers,
or 100,000 followers,
the first thing we need to do
is just identify where you're
at and where is the next progression
within your business.
Same with financials.
If you're making 11K a month,
let's not aim for 100K a month.
How about 12K a month?
That's a great place to go.
And because us fitness professionals know
that within our realm of expertise,
things take time and they are slow,
we're pretty patient.
The other thing is most people think
that progress is linear.
Thinking, "Okay, I'm here now,
and in time I'm going to be here."
But people in the
industry know that not only fat loss,
but also progressions in muscle growth
and performance have many peaks
and troughs.
This could be representative of a diet
break.
This could be representative of a deload.
We make some progress.
We deload the intensity,
so we can go into another phase of
intensity.
Then we deload again,
another phase of intensity.
Then even at the bottom of our deload
here, we are still tremendously better off
than we were before.
In the realm of fat loss, where again,
people think that
progress is linear, in reality,
fat loss looks a lot more like this.
So the same way that for fitness
professionals, we say to our clients, "I
appreciate the weight hasn't moved," or,
"I appreciate that this week shows that
you're up on the scales.
We need to be patient.
We need to focus on the process,
not the outcome." Again, my nan might go,
"James,
this doesn't sound too difficult." "Nan,
we need to focus on the process, not the
outcome." And in the world of fitness,
we can't become obsessed with the outcome.
We actually need to fall in love with the
process, and it's only the people that
fall in love with the process
that achieve the outcome.
This is why I'm so heavy on content
creation, posting
every day.
Because even though posting every day
content creation can seem like
overkill,
and we're about to get into the second
point in a second, so many of my
clients, it was just important
that they came in the gym every day.
It wasn't that they
were coming in the gym every day,
it's that they were doing
something that reminded them of their
journey, of their mission, of what it was
they were trying to accomplish. And
if I could ever get a client to a point
where
skipping the gym for a day made them feel
like they were cheating themselves, the
exact same way that so many people,
if they miss a day posting content,
they feel
disgusted. That, to me,
is indicative of getting someone falling
in love with the
process. Wherever you
are in your business journey, even
if you haven't created
your business yet, that's fine.
Never in my life of the thousands of hours
of PT
sessions did I judge someone for where
they were at.
I would only judge them
if they weren't doing the work necessary
to go from zero to
one.
If they weren't doing the work necessary
to go from where they were on that
box to lower with more weights.
We never judge where someone starts.
We only judge their ethos
and integrity and grit and resilience and
determination from that point on.
Now, the amazing thing is,
someone could walk past in three months'
time and see my
nan doing a completely different exercise,
and they would come to the conclusion,
"Oh, she's strong for an old lady. Oh,
she must be naturally talented.
Oh, your nan's got some mad genetics."
And it's a discredit to the amount of work
you just didn't see behind closed doors.
Every gold medalist Olympian once couldn't
do the thing they did.
Every single swimmer in the Olympics once
couldn't swim.
And it's really important you understand
that.
We are all on our own individual journeys
of competence in different realms.
I have business, being a dad,
training martial arts.
So the ability to progressively overload
is an integral part to operating a good
business.
To not get deflated with where you
are now, to just seek the next
progression. Again, with weight loss.
"Oh, James,
I'd love to lose 10 kilograms." "No,
I think you would like to lose one
kilogram, and we can do
that 10 times." Because then we get to
celebrate 10 times
on the way to your goal rather than one.
Now, the second point,
which really determines whether
or not you'll succeed or
fail,
and why fitness people have this
inclination to become mega wealthy.
Why do people find people that
are in shape sexually attractive?
And why are the majority of
high-functioning CEOs and
business leaders in good shape?
To understand that,
we must look at delayed
gratification. Let's say
when a woman looks at a man
and sees he's in good shape,
she knows there is a certain amount of
self-control.
Every man would love to eat 50,
100 donuts today, but he decides not
to because he knows the implication of
doing that habit over time, days, weeks,
months. Same way
when a man has his finances in check,
it goes to show that he's
long-sighted with his approach to
finances, that he cares about the future.
Because all of the actions
that we take today,
we either have our future in mind or
we don't.
People in the fitness industry know
that if they have a perfect 10 out of
10 workout today, by tomorrow,
they're pretty much no different.
If I'm perfect with my diet today,
by tomorrow,
it's pretty much no different.
Let's use this toilet roll, for example.
If I remove one square,
does it look any different? No,
it looks the exact same.
But if I was to remove one square every
day for a month, noticeably different.
A year, there'd be no tissue left. So
when we return to the pillars,
if you post a
video today, chances
are your business will be no different
tomorrow.
If you post content every day for the next
week, there is little to no chance that
your business will be no different by the
end of the week.
But if you post every day for a year
without caring about what happens today,
but
you care about the accumulation of those
daily processes over the time of a year,
not only can your business look different,
your life can look different.
Email marketing.
If you send an email today to a very small
list, chances are no
difference to your business. But
if you write email marketing emails over
the
course of a year and you pay attention to
open rates, click-through rates,
which emails attributed to the most sales,
which campaigns attributed to the most
sign-ups,
which methodologies of attracting leads,
whether it was from community
posts on LinkedIn, whether it
was a Twitter thread, whether it
was using a ManyChat
automation. Within a week,
you don't know much about your audience,
but within a
year,
your copywriting skills could be
phenomenal,
and your ability to create email
marketing campaigns, whether automated
or broadcasted, can make a massive
difference to your business.
How do you get better at writing emails?
Progressive overload.
How do you get better at making content?
Progressive overload. This
is the crazy part, right?
I've been lifting weights for 20 years.
I look a bit better.
You do this for two, three years,
your life is unrecognizable.
Yet all of you have been training your
weights for 10 years,
but you can't stick to
putting out content
or running an email marketing campaign.
Then maybe a landing page
or your sales page.
Let's think of this like Olympic lifting.
First time you go into a CrossFit gym
and you try Olympic lifting, it's awful.
You catch your nuts with the bar,
hit yourself in the chin, fall over.
But over time, with every single mistake,
you fall forward and you realize, "Hmm,
maybe I shouldn't have done that.
Maybe next time I won't do this.
Maybe I'll put the weight in this part of
my foot." Then if you're a part of a
community like CrossFit,
which I must admit
is fantastic for development, because
in CrossFit communities,
people have a community of people going,
"Actually, do you
know what I found helped when I
was doing it?" "Oh, wow.
I'll give that a go." Sometimes I would
get better advice from fellow CrossFitters
than I would the instructor. Why?
Because the instructor has such a level of
competence that he might not relate to me
in the way that a fellow peer would.
When I arrive in my Discord every morning,
I'm sometimes astounded at the level of
amazing information
that other people within the mentorship
are giving other
people.
The only way you get better at
understanding landing pages is through
creating split tests. Just video.
Video and a little bit of text.
Video with a lot of text.
Us fitness gym bros, we
are always trying to find the
perfect regime.
Although we kind of know we'll never find
it.
And when we discover new information about
how I can lengthen the bicep if I
change the angle here. Wow.
If I use this type of loading pattern,
wow, if I do
this, I might be able to train
that muscle better.
It doesn't really have
that much impact to your life.
But you get this right,
everything's completely different.
I'll explain to you kind of the kicker
that no one's really talking about, which
can be a little bit depressing,
but it should motivate you at the same
time.
Let's say this is your earning potential
as a personal trainer, in person, online.
Let's call this brand diversity.
Your in-person business
is going to be capped
because you're going to sell your time for
hours.
And we're just using this as an example.
You could be a mortgage broker,
yoga instructor,
you could sell real estate.
There's only a certain amount of houses
you can go to and show people around in a
week. With a personal trainer,
there's only a certain amount of hours
that you can
sell for money.
So you're going to be capped by hourly
rate times hours, and that's
where you're going to hit your ceiling of
earning potential.
Then when you go online,
suddenly you're not governed by the same
formula.
Online,
you're capped by the ability to deliver
the service.
So there is going to be a maximum amount
of people in which you can service within
a week,
which is going to be your glass ceiling
here.
But then you can always divide
that by the fact you can hire.
If you hire someone for in person,
it's not a great business model.
You're going to have to give them the
majority of the amount of money that you
make,
and the second they're proficient to do
their own in-person business, they
will leave. Online, when you hire people,
you get to share the one thing that most
people struggle to get, which
is the freedom to work remote.
And for that reason,
they're much less likely to leave you.
We'll get onto the point I'm trying to
make in a second.
And brand diversity
is by the time you've learnt all the
skills you need here and
you've started operating a business
successful here,
you've actually mastered the
hardest part of the entire system,
and here you can pretty much do anything.
If we look at personal trainers,
Sean Casey, Adam Sullivan,
they can put their name
to anything and it will be successful
because they've built the brand.
Chris Williamson is a fantastic podcast
host, and now he has
incredible deals from companies
that have nothing to do with podcasting.
He has a sponsor, Nomatic.
Nomatic make travel suitcases,
fantastic ones. They sent me some.
Amazing.
Because his brand is so strong,
his revenue streams have opened up
everywhere.
For me, three best-selling books,
sold out the Hammersmith Apollo,
sold out the
Sydney Opera House. And the truth is,
because I mastered these two steps,
this is
the hardest part. Once you get to here,
you can quite literally do anything and
it'll probably be successful. But this
is the point I really want to make.
There is an inversion in this. At the top,
I put the term wealth because wealth is
high income, high freedom,
and at the bottom I put difficulty.
And this is where the analogy with fitness
stops.
In fitness, where you begin
is the easiest and it gets harder, and
before you know it,
you're having to do 15 chin-ups,
deadlift twice your body
weight,
and squat twice your body weight to even
stay on top of your progressions.
But in business and in personal brand,
the beginning is the hardest.
This first part in person
is the most difficult with the most
rejection. You have the least skills.
You have the least experience.
You weirdly need the most amount of
tenacity when you have no
reason to have it.
I spent years getting rejected.
"Hey, mate, I've just seen you on the...
Fuck off.
Cheers, you have a good day, mate."
But it is those interactions
and it's those
skills that make everything else so much
easier.
So if I spend a week making a YouTube
video and it bombs,
that's nothing compared
to getting rejected on the gym floor.
The amount of times I offered people free
sessions and they don't show up, the
amount of times you have clients
and they no-show.
The first year is so difficult running
and operating an online
business. Reality,
it's probably going to take you two years
before you can
even get any kind of wind in your sails.
And the reason the personal trainers do so
well in business is this.
Our first year is so grueling
and disgusting.
No one gives a shit,
no one wants to talk to us,
and we pretty much have to fill
out our books before anyone gives us a
modicum of respect.
It took me three and a half years to
really get my PT business to
the point that it was afloat
and successful, and then that
was made up of
one-to-one interview sessions.
Every personal training session
is a one-to-one
meeting, on your feet,
carrying weights in a busy gym with music.
Doof.
Doof. Doof. Doof.
Personal trainers start at altitude
and all we do is we apply the
same principles that we teach people in
fitness to business, and that's why we're
successful. So whatever realm
or industry you're in,
if you can apply the things
I've spoken about today,
you can do so much better.
It's not about where you want to go,
it's about where you are now.
Where's the next progression? Get to work.
Don't think about the impact of what you
do today.
Think about the impact of what you do
today every day for the next year.
The beginning is the hardest part.
You start at altitude.
It's not climbing a mountain where it gets
harder to breathe at the top.
It is the most difficult to breathe at the
very beginning at the base.
By the time you reach the summit,
it's easy going.
But if you cannot implement progressive
overload and you cannot implement delayed
gratification, you
are going to find this so much harder than
it needs to be.
So you deserve to put more work into your
business.
Otherwise, we'll win over your clients,
and all we do is count reps for a living.
Have a good day. If you liked this video,
you've really enjoyed this one that
YouTube recommends you watch. Bye-bye.